<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three questions ansvvered I. Question. What should our meaning be, when after the reading of the fourth Commandement, we pray; Lord incline our hearts to keepe this law? II. Question. How shall the fourth Commandement, being deliuered in such forme of words, binde vs to sanctifie any day, but onely the seauenth, the day wherein God rested, &amp; which the Iewes sanctified? III. Question. How shall it appeare to be the law of nature to sanctifie one day in every weeke?</title>
            <author>Broad, Thomas, 1577 or 8-1635.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16915</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106710</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842422</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842422</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7072</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16915)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7072)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 579:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three questions ansvvered I. Question. What should our meaning be, when after the reading of the fourth Commandement, we pray; Lord incline our hearts to keepe this law? II. Question. How shall the fourth Commandement, being deliuered in such forme of words, binde vs to sanctifie any day, but onely the seauenth, the day wherein God rested, &amp; which the Iewes sanctified? III. Question. How shall it appeare to be the law of nature to sanctifie one day in every weeke?</title>
                  <author>Broad, Thomas, 1577 or 8-1635.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield, and Iames Short printers to the famous Vniversitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Th. Broade.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7072:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THREE QVESTIONS ANSVVERED.</hi>
               <list>
                  <label>I. QVESTION.</label>
                  <item>What ſhould our meaning be, when after the reading of the fourth Commandement, we pray; Lord incline our hearts to keepe this law?</item>
                  <label>II. QVESTION.</label>
                  <item>How ſhall the fourth Commandement, being deliuered in ſuch forme of words, binde vs to ſanctifie any day, but onely the ſeauenth, the day wherein God reſted, &amp; which the Iewes ſanctified?</item>
                  <label>III. QVESTION.</label>
                  <item>How ſhall it appeare to be the Law of Nature to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie one day in every weeke?</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ACT. 20.20.26.27.</bibl>
               <p>I am pure from the blood of all men, for I haue kept backe nothing that was profitable vnto you, but haue decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto you all the counſell of God.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of John Lichfield and James Short, featuring the arms of the University of Oxford (McKerrow 336)</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>SAPIET FELICI</q>
               </head>
               <p>AC: OX</p>
            </figure>
            <p>AT OXFORD, <hi>Printed by IOHN LICHFIELD, and IAMES SHORT</hi> Printers to the famous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie. 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7072:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7072:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE is ſarce any point of doctrine more controverted, then the doctrine of the Sabbath,<note place="margin">Two points of difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs are: when the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth, &amp; what worke may be done therein.</note> as D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bound</hi> telleth vs: indeed, not only we Proteſtants a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelues, but the Papiſts alſo among their ſelues, differ in opinion hereabout. Againe, there is (in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land) iudging one another, there is doing things doubtingly, and there is doing things with offence: which were they to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable in the Church of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul would not haue ſpent a whole chapter about theſe matters. Moreover, whereas the Papiſts praying in latin doe pray without vnderſtanding; many amongſt vs doe pray with a ſinfull vnderſtanding: for as in words, ſo in meaning, they deſire God to incline their hearts to keepe the <hi>7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> day for Sabbath, and to doe no worke therein. Farthermore,<note place="margin">It was printed laſt <hi>1618.</hi>
               </note> ſome in their booke often printed (to ſay nothing of other) haue theſe and the like paſſages: <hi>The 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> commandement is no more Ceremoniall, then all the reſt: the obſervation of the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day is a morall and perpetuall duty: we may not pick vp a few ſticks on the Sabbath: there is aſmuch difference betweene the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
<pb facs="tcp:7072:3"/> and other dayes, as betweene Sacramentall bread and common bread. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The knowledg and conſideration hereof (among other things) cauſeth mee greatly to deſire, that the doctrine of the Sabbath may once at length be throughly diſcuſſed by men of ſound iudgment: and doubtles, what the Scriptures ſentence is in this matter, would ſoone be knowne, were it (as <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> ſometime adviſed) well handled by the learned men of our Vniverſityes:<note place="margin">Act. and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> no man amongſt vs ſhould need any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to halt betweene two opinions, as (the more to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) many of long time haue done, and ſtill doe; yea, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the better order be taken, no doubt will doe even vnto the end of the world.</p>
            <p>Now to provoke herevnto I haue written this little booke: and partly alſo, as hoping it will conduce ſomthing to the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of the trueth, when the time commeth, that it ſhalbe more carefully ſought after which time God haſten for his ſake which is <hi>the trueth,</hi> Ieſus Chriſt; vnto the illumination of whoſe Spirit I commend thee (gentle Reader) and ſo reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in him as long as life laſteth. TH. BROAD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="question">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7072:3"/>
            <head>I. QVESTION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S when the 8. commandement is read, and we pray; <hi>Lord, incline our hearts to keepe this law:</hi> it is all one, as if we ſaid; <hi>Lord, incline our hearts not to ſteale.</hi> So, when the 4. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is read, and we pray; <hi>Lord, incline our hearts to keepe this Law:</hi> it is all one, as if we had ſaid; <hi>Lord, incline our hearts to ſanctifie the Sabbath, to keepe the</hi> 7. <hi>day for Sabbath, and to doe no worke therein:</hi> for this is that law. The <hi>Iewes</hi> had asked this in words and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning both, ſuppoſe they had had the like ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after this commandement: and we muſt needs aske the ſame in words, as they ſhould haue done. The queſtion then is: Whether ſhould we aske the ſame in meaning, as we doe in words; or what ſhould our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning be?</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſwere of ſome in theſe daies.</head>
               <p>By the doctrine of ſome in theſe daies, as in words, ſo in meaning, we ſhould deſire God to incline our hearts to keepe the 7. day for Sabbath, and to doe no worke therein. They teach, that the obſervation of the 7. day is a morall and perpetuall duty: that we may not ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7072:4"/> much as picke vp ſticks in the ſame: and (in a word) that the 4. commandement is no more Ceremoniall, then all the reſt. Now, whereas there is one text principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt them,<note place="margin">Col. 2.16, 17.</note> namely this; <hi>Let no man therefore iudge you in meate, or in drinke, or in reſpect of an holy day, or of the New-moone, or of the Sabbaths: Which are a ſhaddow of things to come, &amp;c:</hi> by <hi>Sabbaths</hi> here they will not haue the weekely Sabbaths meant. But what haue they to ſay? It is <hi>Sabbaths</hi> in the plurall number: and doth not the word <hi>Sabbaths</hi> in the plurall number import the weekely Sabbaths? See <hi>Mat. 28.1. Act. 13, 14.</hi> and <hi>16, 13:</hi> with many other places. This (in my knowledge) is all they haue to ſay; which is ſo little, that it only ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth a will to ſay ſomething: it is not ſo much as <hi>a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> of ſound proofe.</p>
               <p>Conſider (1) that <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul</hi> here vſeth another word, which doth moſt properly ſignifie the Feſtivall daies, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: and therefore it is very vnlikely, that by <hi>Sabbaths</hi> the ſame daies ſhould be meant, as they would haue it: this had beene a needleſſe repetition. (2) Vnleſſe by <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths</hi> here are meant the weekely <hi>Sabbaths:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſtian people choſe the firſt day, and made it their Sabbath, ſayth the booke of Homilies. By the doctrine then of our Church, the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lords day is an Eccles: ordinance, and not an Apoſtol: precept. <hi>Sozom: lib: 5. cap. 8.</hi>
                  </note> what war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant haue we in the Scripture to worke vpon the Iewes Sabbath? Will they ſay, that the Apoſtles command to ſanctifie the Lords day in memory of Chriſts reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection? Be this granted, which cannot be proved, and is ſomething diſcrepant from the doctrine of our Church: doth it therefore follow, that we neede not keepe the 7. day in memory of the worlds creation? <hi>Conſtantine</hi> commanded, that the <hi>6</hi> day ſhould be kept in memory of Chriſts death on the Croſſe: yet was the day of Chriſts reſurrection kept alſo. <hi>Sozomenus</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7072:4"/> that <hi>at Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople, &amp; almoſt in all other places,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Sabbato &amp; poſtridie Sabbati conveniunt:</hi> and in the Scripture wee read of meetings on both daies. It is then a weake ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: The Apoſtles commanded to keepe the firſt day in memory of Chriſts reſurrection: therfore wee neede not keepe the 7 day in memory of the worlds creation. This I would haue thee well to conſider; that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> (of the Apoſtles) is Chriſts only Doctour about dayes: he alone by way of doctrine handleth this point, and he handleth it purpoſly in three ſeverall Epiſtles here; to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> among whom he had never beene;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col. 2. Rom. 14. Gal. 4.</hi> The controverſy about the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath would ſoone be ended, did we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul for a ſufficient Doctour in this matter; as it is great reaſon wee ſhould.</note> and to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> who turned from the Goſpell he had preached vnto them: ſo that he had diverſe times iuſt occaſion to ſhew his minde fully in this matter. Now then, who can belieue, that we need not keepe the Iewes Sabbath (as it is certaine we need not, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues wil acknowledge it) but <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul</hi> ſhould giue vs to vnderſtand aſmuch in one of theſe places, And vnleſſe in this, in none: for in his Epiſtles to the <hi>Romanes</hi> and <hi>Galathians</hi> he ſpeaketh only in a generall manner. True, that generall ſayings here are enough, as in the matter of meates: the law forbad ſwines fleſh, blood, and the like: yet we eate theſe meates, and our warrant is. <hi>Let no man iudge you in your meate or drinke, The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is not meate and drink;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing twiſe of dayes in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall manner, and once in a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; would no doubt haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted the <hi>7</hi> day Sabbath, had it beene to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</note> and ſuch like generall ſayings. So generall ſayings are inough in the matter of daies: but if in this place, where we haue a particular di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the very word <hi>Sabbaths</hi> vſed we ſhal ſay that the weekely Sabbaths are not meant; who will belieue, in other places? The Sabbatharies, which heretofore would haue vs Chriſtians obſerue the Iewes Sabbath,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7072:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> might with more colour put of any text, then this: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this text or none, is of force againſt them. (.3.) Thus it is taken by many great Divines: &amp; S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> termeth the Sabbath <hi>Sacramentum vmbratile, Spirit: &amp; lit: cap: 14.</hi> Againe, in the 15. chapter of that booke, hee termeth the 4 commandement <hi>preceptum figugatum:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inſtit. in <hi>4</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept.</note> and <hi>Calvin</hi> ſayth, <hi>vmbratile veteres nuncupare ſolent:</hi> ſo that it ſeemeth, the Fathers generally by <hi>Sabbaths</hi> here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the weekely Sabbaths, and therfore termed the 4 commandement <hi>vmbratile, ſhadowiſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I haue mervailed, that in theſe dayes two or three (for I know no more in print) ſhould offer to diſſent from ſo many great Divines about the interpretation of this text; eſpecially, having no more to ſay for their owne interpretation. But it ſeemeth, they think, if by Sabbaths here the weekely Sabbaths be meant, then it cannot be avoided but that by <hi>ordinances</hi> in the ſecond verſe before,<note place="margin">Col. 2.14.</note> the precept of the Sabbath muſt alſo bee meant, aſwell as the precepts of the New moone and holy dayes ioyned with it: and thus S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould ſay aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much of the Sabbath &amp; the precept thereof: as he doth ſay or can be ſaid of the new-moon &amp; the precept there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: for more cannot be ſaid of the new moon, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it is a <hi>ſhadow,</hi> nor of the precept thereof, then that it is <hi>an ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce blotted out.</hi> But ſhal I therfore offer to interpret a text wrongfully, becauſe I my ſelfe cannot anſwer an obiection, which may be grounded on it being rightly interpreted? How much better were it to acknowledg mine owne weaknes, and to think, that other happily may vnlooſe that knot which I am not able.</p>
               <p>Beſides this text there are other pregnant inough to proue that the Sabbath was a ſhadow or Ceremony; &amp;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7072:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> conſequently, that the 4 commandement is more Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall, then the reſt. As that text, <hi>Mat: 12.7: But if ye had knowne, what this meaneth, I will haue mercy, and not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, yee would not haue conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned the guiltleſſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">God calleth the Sab. a ſigne, Exod: <hi>31.13.</hi> Chriſt likeneth it to the ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices mat. <hi>12.4.7.</hi> and Paul ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow Col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> Here like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the obſervation of the Sabbath to the offering of ſacrifices: he blameth the Pharyſees, becauſe when God would haue mercy before ſacrifice, they preferred ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice before mercy, that is the keeping of the Sabbath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the feeding of their hungry brethren.</p>
               <p>Againe <hi>Hebr: 4.</hi> In this chapter (<hi>as Marlorate</hi> alſo obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth) mention is made of three Reſts or Sabbaths: one, the firſt ſeventh day, <hi>ver: 4.</hi> another,<note place="margin">A day may be termed Gods Reſt or Sab. in <hi>2</hi> reſpects: firſt becauſe he reſted therin: ſecondly, becauſe it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to his ſervice. In the former reſpect, only the firſt <hi>7</hi> day is gods Sab.</note> the land of Canaan (where Zion was Gods <hi>Reſt for euer Pſal: 132. verſ. 8</hi>) a third, the kingdome of heaven, <hi>verſ. 9.</hi> Now indeed, it is not here ſaid in expreſſe termes, that the 7 day Sabbath, is a text of the heavenly Sabbath: but conſider (.1.) That the Apoſtle in this Epiſtle entreateth much of types, &amp; and of that whereof they were types. (2.) If the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> (Gods locall reſt in this world) were a type of the reſt in heaven as all acknowledg: then likewiſe the 7 day (Gods te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall Reſt in this world) as ſpoken of here both together, and in the ſame manner. (.3.) The 7 day &amp; the kingdome of heauen haue one common name,<note place="margin">Gods Reſts in this world were two: the one of the time, the, <hi>7th</hi> day the other, of place; the land of Canaan.</note> 
                  <hi>Reſt or Sabbath:</hi> &amp; the reſemblance between them is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, as betweene the ſacrifices of beaſts in the time of the law, and that ſacrifice of Chriſt on the Croſſe. As God reſted on the 7 day after his works in the 6 daies: as the Iſraelites reſted on the 7 day after their works in the 6 dayes: ſo ſhall the godly reſt in heaven after their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and miſeryes in this world, <hi>Bleſsed are the dead, which dye in the Lord, for they reſt from their Labours.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 14.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:7072:6"/>
               <p>Some that acknowledge the 7 dayes Sabbath to be a type or ſhadow, will haue it ſuch in reſpect of <hi>the ſtrict reſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Paul would not haue ſaid that the holy dayes, new-moone and Sab. were a ſhadow; if not theſe, but circumſtances only about them, had beene a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. If it were a ſhadow becauſe it was the laſt of the weeke: then belike the new-moone was a ſhadow becauſe it was the firſt of the month.</note> and that it was <hi>the laſt of ſeven:</hi> but I doubt not the 7 day Sabbath was a ſhadow of the Sabbath <hi>to come,</hi> inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it was a Sabbath that is a day of Reſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing. And ſo was the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> a type of the kingdome of heaven, inaſmuch as it was a place of Reſt after the Egyptian-bondage, and weariſome iourny through the wildernes. The like may be ſaid of the new-moone and Feaſts ioyned with the Sabbath, <hi>Col. 2.</hi> they were all in likelihood a ſhadow of the ſame thing to come, the kingdome of heaven; and in one and the ſame reſpect, I meane, in being times of Reſting, Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and reioycing. Againe, ſome that acknowledge the ſeaventh day Sabbath for a ſhaddow, will not haue it ſuch from the beginning: but when as all other types and ſhaddowes were ſuch from their firſt inſtitution,<note place="margin">The very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Iewes Sab. was typicall: for God ſanctified the <hi>7</hi> day becauſe he had reſted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</note> who will belieue them without manifeſt proofe? And ſhall I demaunde of them, when the 7 day Sabbath became a ſhadow, and which was the firſt Sabbath that was ſuch; I doubt not, wee ſhould all enter into the heavenly Sabbath before they would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree vpon an anſwer to this queſtion. Obſerue, that the Apoſtle <hi>Hebr: 4, 4,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">I ſay, if not in time: for in like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood God did not ſanct. the <hi>7</hi> day, before the firſt <hi>7</hi> day was ended. Note theſe words, Gen. <hi>2.3.</hi> becauſe in it he had reſted, not, would reſt.</note> ſpeaketh of the 7 day, as reſted vpon by God; and not, as ſanctified by him, or inioyned to be ſanctified of man: ſo that the 7 day then became a type, when God reſted therein. The 7 day in order (if not in time) before it was ſanctified, was Gods <hi>Reſt,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, a ſhaddow of <hi>the reſt remaining to the people of God.</hi> But this, by way of diſgreſſion: to returne.</p>
               <p>Inough hath beene ſaid to make it appeare, that the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7072:6"/> 4 commandement is more Ceremonial, then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and therefore not (as the other) to be obſerved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the letter: only I will add for a concluſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t ſaying of Auguſtine; <hi>Quiſquis illum diem (Sabbatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervat ſicut litera ſonat, carnaliter ſapit, that is,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Spig. &amp; lit. cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Whoſoeuer obſerveth the Sabbath, as the letter ſoundeth ſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of the fleſh.</hi> Now they which keepe the 7 day, &amp; doe no worke therein, keepe the ſabbath, as the letter of the precept ſoundeth. Their <hi>Handwriting</hi> then ſhould haue beene <hi>blotted out,</hi> and not put in print, who teach, that the obſervation of the 7 day is a morall and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall duty, and that we may not ſo much as pick vp ſticks in the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſwere agreeable to the Doctrine of our Church.</head>
               <p>When the 8 commandement is read, and wee pray,<note place="margin">So, for the reſt of the comman.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, incline our hearts to keepe this Law,</hi> our words and meaning muſt agree; as in words, ſo in meaning, wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire grace not to ſteale: but here, not ſo. Though in words we deſire God to incline our hearts to keepe the 7 day for Sabbath, and to doe no worke therein, yet not in meaning. It is ſaid in the booke of Homylies, that whatſoever is found in the 4 commandement appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the law of nature,<note place="margin">The <hi>4</hi> comman. bound the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites to do that, which they were not bound to doe by the law of nature: but not vs Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. This is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon doctrine</note> ought to be obſerved of all good Chriſtians: our meaning then after the doctrine of our Church ſhould be thus: <hi>Lord, incline our hearts to keepe this law, ſo far forth as it is the Law of nature.</hi> Or thus: <hi>Lord incline our hearts to keepe ſo much of this Law as apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to the law of nature: which is the ſame in effect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus haue I anſwered a very needfull queſtion in my
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7072:7"/> opinion: what other will iudge of this matter, I know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>t for mine owne part I iudge it ſo needfull to be knowne,<note place="margin">Our Church hath taken order for the nſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in this mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, I meane, by the booke of Homilyes: but in theſe dayes ſew pariſhes haue that booke; in fewer it is read; and where ttis read, ſcarce one in an hundred (I feare) lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a right meaning by it.</note> that with <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul I would gladly ſpend &amp; be ſpent</hi> to bring my ignorant brethren to a right meaning here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s it not a lamentable caſe, when a man prayeth, <hi>Lord in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e mine heart to keepe the 7 day for Sabbath and to doe no worke therein</hi> to meane according to his word; which is to obſerue a ſhadow; and this, a kind of deniall that Chriſt is come? The Papiſts pray without vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but ſuch pray with a ſinfull vnderſtanding. And if by ſome triall I may make coniecture, thus doe the greateſt part of this kingdome: neyther is it any mervaile, if very many ſo doe, when they are ſo taught by ſome in theſe dayes. Againe, I finde by experience, that they wil hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be brought to a right meaning here: it ſeemeth to them ſo ſtrange, that in the Publike Service one thing ſhould be ſpoken, and another mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; as that they ſhould heare, <hi>the 7 day is the Sabbath,</hi> when not the 7 day, but the firſt day muſt be kept by them. And when to make them take more heed, I tell them, that to keepe the 7 day for Sabbath, and to doe no worke therein (as the words of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement are) is <hi>to ſavour of the fleſh,</hi> which <hi>is death</hi> in the iudgment of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Auguſtine</hi> and other learned Divines:<note place="margin">Sapere ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum carnem mors eſt. <hi>Spir. &amp; lit. cap.</hi> 14.</note> this maketh them even to ſtand amazed at the ſtrangnes of the matter. Moreover, as it is hard to bring them to, ſo no doubt will it be to keepe them in a right meaning; theſe words, <hi>the</hi> 7 <hi>day is the Sabbath,</hi> and, <hi>in it thou ſhalt doe no worke,</hi> ſtill ſounding in their eares. Which I write to this end, that my brethren may be more carefull often to ingeminate vnto their Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners the doctrine of our Church delivered in the booke
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7072:7"/> of Homilyes. Truely, if ever, it had here need be, as the Prophet <hi>Eſaie</hi> ſpeaketh; <hi>precept vpon precept, precept vpon precept, line vpon line, line vpon line, here a little,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſai 28.10.</note> 
                  <hi>and there a little:</hi> or rather indeed <hi>here a great deale, and there a great deale;</hi> and yet I feare mee <hi>all to little,</hi> as would be found vpon triall afterward.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="question">
            <head>II. QVESTION.</head>
            <p>IN the iudgment of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Auguſtine</hi> we Chriſtians are bound by the 4 commandement to keepe a figuratiue or ſpirituall Sabbath:<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>99.</hi> ad Ianuar.</note> 
               <hi>Inter omnia illa decem precepta &amp;c. Among all thoſe ten precepts, that alone, which is there placed of the Sabbath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul: adver: iud.</note> 
               <hi>is commanded figuratiuely to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</hi> Thus <hi>Tertullian</hi> termeth Chriſt (whom, as <hi>the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Sonne</hi> wee muſt heare <hi>Mat. 17. Hebr. 1.) Sabbati ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualis cultorem:</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaying, that <hi>Legis iuſtitia prima &amp; ſalutaris decem habet mandata,</hi> ſetteth downe this for the 4, <hi>Cole Sabbatum ſpirituale,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cited by Muſ: loc. commun.</note> 
               <hi>keepe a ſpirituall Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is according to <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and other (as I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in my little reading) a twofold keeping of thoſe commandements touching the Sabbath, circumciſion,<note place="margin">There are two ſorts of Sabbath, after Auguſtine and other: the one literall, carnall, or temporall: the other figuratiue, ſpirituall, and eternall.</note> ſacrifices, and the like the one, literall or carnall: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, figuratiue or ſpirituall. Now the Iſraelites were bound to keepe theſe in a literall manner, that is, to doe no worke on the 7 day, to circumciſe on the 8 day, &amp; to offer lambs and ſuch like in ſacrifice to the Lord: We Chriſtians are bound to keepe theſe in a figuratiue or ſpirituall manner, that is, to reſt from the works of our
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7072:8"/> corrupt nature all the dayes of the worke, to circumciſe the foreſkins of our hearts, and to offer ſpirituall ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of praiſe &amp; thankſgiuing. Theſe two kinds of bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (figuratiue and literall) I obſerue in <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Augustine,</hi> and ſome other: but by the common doctrine in theſe dayes there is a third, of that commandement touching the Sabbath though not of the other; namely, <hi>partly</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall; for it bindeth vs to ſanctifie one day of the weeke.</p>
            <p>But there a queſtion may wel be demanded. How ſhal the 4 commandement being delivered in ſuch forme of words, binde vs to ſanctifie any day, but only the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth? Suppoſe, that Chriſt had ſaid to his Diſciples: <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the day of Reſurrection to ſanctifie it: ſixe dayes of the weeke ye ſhall labour, and doe all that ye haue to doe; but the first day is the day of Reſurrection: in it you ſhall doe &amp;c.</hi> How ſhould this commandement binde vs to ſanctifie any day, but onely the firſt, the day of Reſurrection? So God ſaying: <hi>Remember the ſabbath</hi> (or, <hi>day of Reſt) to ſanctifie it: 6 dayes ſhalt thou labour, &amp; doe al that thou haſt to doe; but the 7 day is the Sabbath &amp;c.</hi> How ſhould this commandement binde vs to ſanctifie any day but onely the ſeaventh, the day wherein God reſted, and which the Iewes ſanctified?</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin">I haue thought good thus to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold the <hi>4</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement for the better vnderſtanding of that which followeth.</note>Anſwere of a great Divine heretofore.</head>
               <p>In the 4 commandement we haue to obſerue (.1.) The commandement it ſelfe briefly delivered, &amp; is thus: Remember the Sabbath to ſanctifie it. (.2.) Then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth an Explication in order, God ſhewing firſt,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7072:8"/> which is the Sabbath; <hi>the ſeventh day is the Sabbath to the Lord thy God:</hi> and after, how it is ſanctified; in it thou ſhalt doe no worke (.3.) Laſtly a reaſon is yeelded, why God requireth this ſervice:<note place="margin">Redem: in <hi>4</hi> precept.</note> for in ſixe dayes the Lord made &amp;c. Thus <hi>Zanchius</hi> in effect; thus <hi>Virell</hi> likewiſe in his <hi>Grounds of Religion: and this analiſis</hi> of the 4 com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is ſo naturall that every one of vnpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall iudgement muſt needes approue it and I could wiſh that ſuch as vndertake to handle the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, would take notice of it.</p>
               <p>So then, this is (for ſubſtance) the whole 4 comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement; <hi>Remember the Sabbath to ſanctifie it:</hi> as for that which followeth, it is eyther an explication, or a Reaſon. Here now the word <hi>Sabbath</hi> a great Divine would haue taken in a generall ſence: ſo that God ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>Remember the Sabbath to ſanctifie it;</hi> That thou maiſt the better conceaue his meaning. Suppoſe, God had ſaid to the Iſraelites; <hi>Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber to honour your King, &amp; Saul is your kinge:</hi> When Saul was dead, and David come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his place; this commandement, <hi>Remember to hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our your kinge,</hi> had bound them ſtill, aſmuch to honour David now, as Saul before. So, God ſaying; <hi>Remember the Sabbath to ſanctifie it, and the 7 day is the Sabbath:</hi> when the 7 day ceaſed to be the Sabbath, &amp; the firſt day came in his place; this commandement, <hi>Remember the Sabbath to ſanctifie it,</hi> may binde aſwell to ſanctifie the firſt day now, as it did the 7 day heretofore. Thus teacheth a great Divine: but I cannot eaſily ſubſcribe herevnto. In my opinion God ſaying, <hi>Remember the Sabbath to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it;</hi> is all one, as if he had ſaid, <hi>Remember the</hi> 7 <hi>day to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7072:9"/> ſanctifie it.</hi> The Sabbath is the 7 day, and the 7 day is the Sabbath, in the ſcriptures: many reaſons there are, which will not ſuffer vs to approue his doctrine.</p>
               <p n="1">(.1.) The dayes of the weeke may be named thus; the firſt day, the ſecond day &amp;c. or thus, <hi>the day of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting light, the day of creating the firmament &amp;c.</hi> As now <hi>the firſt day,</hi> and <hi>the day of creating light,</hi> are the ſame: ſo likewiſe, <hi>the ſeaventh day,</hi> and <hi>the day of Reſt.</hi> And this appeareth to be the iudgment of <hi>Auguſtine, Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">So likewiſe it is taken in ſome Courts: a proces citing to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare <hi>dic Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bati,</hi> is vpon Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turday.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian &amp;c.</hi> ſeeing in their books by the <hi>Sabbath</hi> is meant the 7 day, and by <hi>the Lords day</hi> is meant the firſt: for otherwiſe they would haue vſed the names of <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> and <hi>Lords day</hi> for one &amp; the ſame day of the weeke. (.2.) By the word <hi>Sabbath</hi> in the end of the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement muſt needes be meant the 7 day only. For ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue: <hi>and reſted the</hi> 7 <hi>day; wherefore the Lord bleſſed the Sabbath, &amp; ſanctified it.</hi> Here thou ſeeſt, that Gods reſting on the 7 day, is the reaſon, wherefore he ſanctified the Sabbath: and can it be a reaſon of ſanctifiing any other day beſides the ſeventh; eſpecially, when he laboured on all the other?<note place="margin">The reaſon of the <hi>7</hi> dayes in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitution va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed as a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow with the ſhadow.</note> Suppoſe, we had the like ſpeech in the New Teſtament, as thus: <hi>He roſe againe vpon the firſt day; wherefore he bleſſed the day of Reſurrection, and ſanctified it:</hi> who would not take <hi>the day of Reſurrection</hi> here for the firſt day only? Adde, that were not <hi>Sabbath</hi> &amp; <hi>ſeventh day</hi> the ſame, it ſhould rather haue beene ſaid; <hi>Wherefore the Lord bleſſed the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day,</hi> or <hi>this Sabbath;</hi> then the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> Againe, it is ſaid, <hi>bleſſed the Sabath,</hi> the meaning is, in the beginning: and now turne to <hi>Gen. 2.</hi> and there it is ſaid, that God <hi>bleſſed</hi> the 7 day, and ſanctified it. Theſe words
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7072:9"/> then, <hi>Sabbath</hi> and <hi>ſeventh day,</hi> are vſed <hi>promiſcuè</hi> in the Scripture (.3.) By this doctrine the 4 commandement ſhould be of larger extent, then that commandement in the beginning (ſuppoſe, it were a commandement as ſome will haue it:) for there it is ſaid, God bleſſed the 7 day, not, the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> (.4.) Thus ſhould the 4 comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement conſiſt of a generall commandement, and a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular the generall, <hi>Remember the Sabbath to ſanctifie it:</hi> the particular, <hi>The 7 day ſhall be the Sabbath.</hi> (5) Had they who firſt appointed that order of reading the 4 com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and the people praying after, beene of this iudgment: they would mee thinks haue put <hi>the firſt</hi> in place of the ſeventh, the firſt day, and not the 7, being now the Sabbath to the Lord our God. Suppoſe, God had given this commandement to the Iſraelites: <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to honour your kinge, and Saul is your kinge.</hi> This commandement being read in the Synagogues, and the people praying after; <hi>Lord haue mercy on vs &amp;c.</hi> when Saul was dead, and David kinge; would they haue ſtill read the commandement in the ſame forme of words, <hi>Remember to honour your kinge, and Saul is your kinge?</hi> I cannot belieue it. They then no doubt, who firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed this order in the Church, tooke the Sabbath &amp; the 7 day for the ſame in the 4 commandement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſweres of other in theſe dayes.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>1</label> That the <hi>Sabbath</hi> and the 7 day are the ſame, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by ſome other in theſe dayes: but they would haue the word <hi>ſeventh</hi> taken in a generall ſence;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7072:10"/> ſo that (I conceaue) they would haue the 4 commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment read thus. <hi>Remember the Sabbath to ſanctifie it &amp;c. ſixe daies &amp;c. but a ſeventh day is the Sabbath &amp;c</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto my anſwere is (.1.<note place="margin">A ſeventh day, that is, one of ſeven; as I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them.</note>) That the word truly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly tranſlated, is <hi>the ſeuenth</hi> for the particle is there vſed: neyther I belieue, did any ever tranſlate it otherwiſe (.2.) Thus ſhould the word be taken in one ſence in the beginning of the commandement; and in another, afterward.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> For after it is ſaid; <hi>and reſted on the 7 day:</hi> here by <hi>ſeuenth day</hi> muſt needes be meant one certaine day. (.3.) If God ſanctified a ſeventh day, then he made man on a ſixth day; &amp; were not this to confound every dayes worke? (.4) The ſame word is vſed <hi>Gen. 2;</hi> and there it muſt be tranſlated <hi>the ſeuenth day:</hi> for it were abſurd to ſay,<note place="margin">in it.</note> 
                  <hi>God bleſſed a 7 day, becauſe he reſted on the 7 day:</hi> if God bleſſed a <hi>ſeuenth day,</hi> then he reſted vpon <hi>a 7 day, Gen. 2. verſ. 3.</hi> (.5.) Thus ſhould not god from Sinai appoint, what day of the weeke the Iſraelites ſhould ſanctifi; &amp; ſo indeed writeth a reverend Divine; <hi>It was never commanded nor appointed, what one certaine day ſhould bee kept among ſeaven, but that there ſhould be obſerved a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day.</hi> But ſhould Paul haue taught in the Iewes Synagogues, that God from Sinai did no more appoint their day to be ſanctified, then ours; and that Chriſtians ſanctified the Lords day, kept the 4 commandement ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the letter, aſmuch as they: I leaue it to other to conſider, what would haue followed therevpon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>2</label> There are other againe which will haue it read, the 7 day is the <hi>Sabbath to the</hi> &amp;c. but yet by their doctrine any day of the weeke may be meant hereby, and with them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7072:10"/> the Lords day is the ſeventh.<note place="margin">That the Lords day is, and muſt be, the <hi>7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </hi> day; beginneth to be ſomthing a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon doctrine.</note> Thus a learned Preacher wrote vnto mee. <hi>The 7 day alone is ſanctified, but the Lord hath not aſſigned any immutable Date of time, from which this 7 muſt be reckoned:</hi> for he never ſayth in any place, <hi>God ſanctified the 7 from ſuch or ſuch a Date. So the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of that number is immutable, but the taking of one only beginning,</hi> from which to begin the account is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable: <hi>had it beene, the Apoſtles, in whoſe time the chang of Dates began, would ſure haue knowne it, and not ſuffered ſuch chang without reproof.</hi> This I receaued from a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Preacher. Now, vnto thoſe his words; <hi>for he neuer ſayth in any place, God ſanctified &amp;c.</hi> my anſwere is, That he had no need ſo to ſay, unleſſe there had beene more then ſixe dayes before the firſt ſeventh, or that hee had bleſſed any other ſeaventh day ſince. Neyther of which being ſo, the Date muſt needes bee from the day, wherein God ſeparated the light from the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: and what more certaine Date of time, from whence to beginne the reckoning, then from the beginning of the creation, before which there was no time at all? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, whereas he ſayth, <hi>that the change of Dates began in the Apoſtles dayes:</hi> I would know, where this doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. Rather the contrary appeareth:<note place="margin">Act: 20. 1. Cor. 16.</note> for by the <hi>firſt of the weeke</hi> (as themſelues ſay) is meant the Lords day. See then, the ancient Date of time is continued by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: for if the Lords day were the firſt of the weeke, the Iwes Sabbath muſt needes be the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and laſt of the weeke in the Apoſtles time, as it was in the beginning.</p>
               <p>I haue much mervailed, wherefore ſome muſt nedes haue the Lords day be the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, ſo contrary to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7072:11"/> who terme it the firſt of the weeke in two places: and at the mouth of two witneſſes we would thinke, this matter ſhould be eſtabliſhed. But it ſeemeth, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Gen. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Iacob haue I bleſſed, &amp; he ſhalbe bleſſed:</hi> ſo they thinke; God bleſſed the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day, and it muſt be bleſſed: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnleſſe the Lords day come to be the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, it is not bleſſed &amp; ſanctified. But they ſhould conſider, that God did not bleſſe the day,<note place="margin">The Lords day will come to be the <hi>7</hi> when Eſau commeth o be Iacob.</note> becauſe it was the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> had he, then were it ſome reaſon, that the name and bleſſing ſhould ſtill goe together: but now, he bleſſed the day, becauſe he had reſted therein; and if theſe two may be ſundered, much more the other. What God hath put aſunder, let not man ioyne together,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.3</note> Lords day and ſeventh day: it will not procure them a bleſſing to goe about in ſuch ſort to maintaine the trueth. If their doctrine can other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be maintained, I deſire them in Chriſts name, that they would if their doctrine cannot otherwiſe be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, I admoniſh them in the feare of God to teach ſuch doctrine, as may. Were it once receaved that wee muſt ſanctifie the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day; and they, neyther by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, reaſon, nor Fathers can proue, that the day we doe now ſanctifie, is the ſeventh: will it not come to paſſe, that we ſhall fall back to the Iewes day? The Scripture is againſt them: and that in two places. <hi>Act. 20. 1. Cor. 16,</hi> Reaſon is againſt them: for if the Iewes Sabbath vntill the change were the 7, how ſhould the next day be the ſeventh alſo? the name <hi>ſeventh</hi> hath reference to other dayes going before: ſhall one and the ſame day bee the ſeventh of one weeke, and the ſixth of the next weeke? Now, among the Fathers, <hi>Ierome</hi> is againſt them, for he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7072:11"/> termeth Wedneſday <hi>the fourth of the weeke: Si dies obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vare non licet, &amp; menſes, &amp; tempora, &amp; annos; nos quoque ſimile crimen incurrimus, quartam Sabbati obſervantes, &amp; Paraſceven, &amp; diem Dominicam &amp;c.</hi> Com: in Ep: ad Gal: cap: 4.</p>
               <p>Finally, by this anſwere, as by the former, the word <hi>ſeventh</hi> ſhould be taken in one ſence in the beginning of the commandement, and in another afterward for after it is ſaid, <hi>and reſted on the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day.</hi> Here by <hi>ſeventh day</hi> muſt needs be meant one certaine day: no man will ſay, that God reſted on the day, we now keepe holy. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if by <hi>ſeventh day Ex. 20.</hi> any day be meant aſwell as Saturday: by <hi>firſt day Act: 20.</hi> why ſhall not any day be meant, aſwell as Sunday? But not to ſtand longer herea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout: this laſt anſwere cannot ſtand without the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of Gods weeke: that it may be receaved, God had need to make the world againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A likelier anſwere, then either of the former.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> on Gen. 2. hath theſe words. <hi>Iam hìc ab i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitio doctrinam hanc nobis inſinuat Deus &amp;c. Here from the beginning God doth inſinuate this doctrine, that one day in the circle of the weeke ſhould be ſevered for ſpirituall worke.</hi> Note the word <hi>inſinuateth. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Field</hi> hath theſe words in his 5 booke, and 29 chapter. <hi>Preſuppoſing the knowledg of the creation, reaſon convinceth vs, that one day of ſeven muſt be a day of reſt. Reaſon convinceth.</hi> Some ſuch thing I thinke muſt be ſaid here: as that God by giving this commandement to the Iſraelites, doth <hi>inſinuate,</hi> that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7072:12"/> Chriſtians ſhould ſanctifie one day of the weeke. Or thus: Inaſmuch as God, having choſen to himſelfe a Church commanding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, after 6 dayes labour to ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the 7 day; <hi>reaſon convinceth,</hi> or this is an argument, that it is Gods will, we Chriſtians (now his Church) ſhould doe in ſome ſort, as the Iſraelites by the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement were bound to doe heretofore. The 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> commandement bindeth vs to ſanctifie one day of the weeke: that is, It bindeth vs to belieue, that it is Gods will, we ſhould ſanctifie one day of the weeke; ſeing (as thereby it appeareth) he once appointed the Iſraelites after 6 dayes labour to ſanctifie the ſeventh day, &amp; the ſame reaſons in part ſtill continue.</p>
               <p>To end this matter. Were it a law of this kingdome ſet forth long agone in theſe words: <hi>Remember to faſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Thurſday;</hi> We in theſe times faring well vpon Thurſday, &amp; faſting vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> friday; ſome man ſhould ſay, that the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named law bound vs ſo to doe; &amp; vnleſſe we did faſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Friday, we brake that Statute: who hearing this, would not be much moved at the ſtrangenes of the matter, &amp; preſently demand; How ſhall this be, ſeing the Statute ſpeaketh of Thurſday? How can ſuch a Statute binde vs to faſt vpon Friday? Now, how the like vnto this may be, I haue ſhewed with the beſt ſkill I haue: and if any thinke my ſkill herein defectiue, and ſay; Never any law of God or man did binde in ſuch manner, as you ſpeake of. I muſt confeſſe it, in my knowledge: but did ever any other law of God or man appoint a thinge to be done on one day of the weeke, and binde to doe it on another day; or appoint a thinge to be done in one place, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7072:12"/> binde to doe it in another place? Such a law (if there were ever any ſuch) did binde in ſuch manner, as I ſpeake of: or if any hath more ſkill to anſwere this queſtion, I greatly deſire him to ſhew his ſkill. The queſtion is ſuch, as we would thinke, every one of the meaneſt vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding would demand it firſt of all: and it is made a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full queſtion to be anſwered, by reaſon of thoſe ſtrange interpretations of Gods word aforemencioned, I mean that the Sabbath and ſeauenth day are not the ſame in the fourth Commandement: againe that by ſeauenth day in the fourth commandement any day of the week may be ſignified. Should way bee giuen to ſuch inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations of the Scripture, who ſeeth not what would follow therevpon? It doth not a little moue me, when in Proteſtant writers I read ſuch paſſages as this; <hi>It was neuer commanded nor appointed, what one certaine day ſhould be kept among ſeauen, &amp;c.</hi> Conſider well of the matter, and thou wilt ſay, that I am not moued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="question">
            <head>III QVESTION.</head>
            <p>HOW ſhall it appeare to be the law of Nature to ſanctifie one day in every weeke?</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſwere.</head>
               <p>Almighty God having in 6 dayes created the heaven and the earth, reſted vpon the 7 day,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.3.</note> and therfore ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied it; as is ſaid, <hi>Gen: 2.</hi> Hence now ſome would gather,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7072:13"/> that it is the law of nature to ſanctifie one day in euery weeke: but indeed it will hence rather follow, that it is the law of nature to ſanctifie the preciſe ſeauenth day. Vpon theſe premiſes: God made the world in ſix daies, and reſting on the ſeauenth day ſanctified it; by the light of nature or reaſon this inference ſhould rather bee made: therefore it is the law of nature to ſanctifie the ſeauenth day. Then doe we moſt neerely follow Gods example, when we worke vpon thoſe very dayes, which he wrought vpon; and ſanctifie that very day, which he ſanctified. God in the beginning ſanctified the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day: therefore it is the law of nature to ſanctifie the ſeauenth day; is a neerer inference than that other: therefore it is the law of nature to ſanctifie one day of the ſeauen or weeke. The like may be ſaid touching the placing of the fourth commandement among the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, if any would fetch an argument thence to prooue this matter.</p>
               <p>In the 2 to the Romans Paul ſaith, <hi>That the Gentiles did by nature the things contained in the Law,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2:14.</note> 
                  <hi>and were a law to themſelues:</hi> From which text happily an argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t might be fetched to proue as much the law of nature, as M. <hi>Dod</hi> affirmeth, that is, <hi>to haue ſolemne times;</hi> for ſo the Gentiles had: but now the Gentiles ſanctified not one day in euery weeke. It will rather follow from the practiſe of the Gentiles, that it is the law of nature to haue a place appointed, than one day in euery weeke appointed for publike meetings: the Gentiles had Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.14.</note>In the 1 Cor. 11. S. Paul hath theſe words: <hi>Doth not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7072:13"/> even nature it ſelfe teach you, that if a man hath long haire, it is a ſhame vnto him?</hi> Now ſhould I ſay in like manner, doth not euen nature it ſelfe teach vs to ſanctifie one day in euery weeke? For one that would affirme, many I thinke at firſt would deny, that nature taught it them, they ſee no ſuch thing by the light of nature, they had neuer any naturall inclination to ſanctifie one day of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſeauen. But though at firſt euery man will be ready thus to ſay, yet vpon conſideration happily, it will ſeem the beſt order: and if we ſee by <hi>The light in vs</hi> (whereof Chriſt ſpeaketh Mat. 6.<note place="margin">Though it be not by any expreſſe command from Chriſt or his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, but by an ordinance of the Church (as is the doctrine of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great Diuines, &amp; of our church in the booke of Homilies) that we ſanctifie the Lords day, rather then another day in the weeke: yet can I maintaine, that it is the law of Nature to ſanctifie this very day; for it is <hi>The beſt order.</hi> And this I think no man of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will once offer to deny; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe perhaps, becauſe ſome hold a ſuperſtitious conceit of the day.</note>) that it is the beſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſanctifie one day in euery weeke; then me thinks it may bee ſaid, that nature doth teach vs ſo to doe. <hi>Let all things</hi> (ſaith Paul) <hi>be done decently and in order,</hi> 1. Cor. 14. This command of Paul is the very law of nature: <hi>doth not euen nature it ſelfe teach</hi> vs as much? The beſt order is the will of God, and the law of nature. This is it then which I ſay. <hi>If reaſon, the light in vs,</hi> or <hi>Nature</hi> (for theſe I take for the ſame) teacheth it to bee the beſt order to ſanctifie one day in euery weeke, then is it to bee held the law of nature ſo to doe: but <hi>Reaſon, the light in vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">What the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers tearme <hi>Reaſon;</hi> Chriſt tearmeth <hi>The light in vs;</hi> and Paul, <hi>Nature.</hi>
                  </note> or <hi>Nature</hi> teacheth it to bee the beſt order to ſanctifie one day in every weeke: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is to be held the law of nature ſo to doe. This is the only argument to prooue this matter.</p>
               <p>But here are two things, which I thinke good to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe thee of One is, that we ſhould not tearme it <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> to ſanctifie one day in the weeke, though it bee the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7072:14"/> law of nature ſo to doe. Some would haue the Morall law and the law of Nature to be the ſame: but when they haue better conſidered the matter, I doubt not, they will be of another minde. The law of nature (to diſtinguiſh of it ſo farre forth as concerneth the preſent purpoſe,<note place="margin">The la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is partly morall, &amp; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly circumſtantial</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> twofold. Firſt, the law of nature bindeth vs to performe Morall duties, as to pray, giue almes &amp;c. every one by the light of nature knoweth, that he muſt doe good, vertuous, and godly actions to his power. Secondly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of nature bindeth vs to obſerue cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> time and place, about the performance of morall duties; that good may then and there be done when and where it is beſt to bee done: and this againe we all knowe by the light of nature in vs. Now then, inaſmuch as the law of nature bindeth vs to performe morall duties, let it be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed morall: it is a morall law of nature to pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> to giue almes, to relieue the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed &amp;c. But inaſmuch as the law of nature bindeth vs to obſerue circumſtances, as time and place, about the performance of morall vertues, it ſhould in my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding be tearmed <hi>circumſtantiall.</hi> Time, as place, is a Circumſtance; &amp; therefore I cannot like, that a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, whereby the obſeruation of any time is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, ſhould be tearmed morall: it properly belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto thoſe commandements, whereby morall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are inioyned. And this ſeemeth to bee the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our moſt iudicious Divine D. <hi>Field,</hi> who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth the fourth commandement out of the number of the Moralls, <hi>booke 5. chap. 22.</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath their words, in Galat. cap. 3. <hi>Scine priùs debet quis, &amp;c. We ought
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7072:14"/> firſt to knowe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>kes of the law are twofold, for part belong vnto S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd part vnto manners. Vnto the Sacraments th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ircumciſion of the fleſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note that hee ſaith the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Sabath;</hi> and not only <hi>the litterall,</hi> or <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Sabbath t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he, ſacrifices, and innumerable ſuch like obſeruat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> into mann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Thou ſhalt not kill; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhalt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>it adultery; Thou ſhalt not beare falſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> If now the temporall Sabbath did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nners: if a Jew ſanctifying his Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me a morall duty; then is it not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e day of the weeke: for the ſeauenth day to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Iewes was, as this law of nature it ſelfe, ſeeing they laboured all the ſix daies going before. If the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Sabbath belongeth not to manners, neither doth ours: for ours is aſwell temporall, as the Iewes, though not ſo litterall or ſhadowiſh; ours is no more eternall, then theirs was.</p>
               <p>The other thinge, which I thinke good to advertiſe thee of, is; that though it be the law of nature to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie one day of every weeke: yet not abſolutely, but after a ſort. After a ſort; for it is moſt commonly the beſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: not abſolutely; for it is not alwayes the beſt order. One and the ſame order cannot be beſt at all times and in all places: circumſtances alter matters of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; ſo that, what Nature teacheth vs to doe at one time, it may forbid vs to doe at another time.<note place="margin">This which is a circumſtantiall law of nature one yeare, may not bee ſuch the next yeare.</note> To in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: the laſt yeare of Kinge Edward the ſixt, Nature taught the godly (it was the beſt order) to meete at ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed times in publick Temples, there to pray, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the Sacraments &amp;c. but the next yeare following, being the firſt of Queene Mary, Nature or Reaſon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7072:15"/> them ſo to doe, and taught them to meete, when with ſafety they might, in private houſes, fields, or woods, as they did in the Primitiue Church during the times of perſecution: this was then the beſt order. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the abſolute Lawes of Nature may not be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in caſe of neceſſity: a man may not forſweare him ſelfe, lye, or ſteale, to ſaue his life: but to ſaue the liues of his cattell a man may labour all the week and make e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day working day. The Sabbath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid before) was to the Iſraelites, as this law of Nature: nay, it was more;<note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> for <hi>the Sabbath was a ſhadow of things to come:</hi> yet in caſe of neceſſity the Iſraelites might breake and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane the Sabbath, as in the time of the Macchabees ſome intended to doe.<note place="margin">1. Mac. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>The Sabbath</hi> (as Chriſt ſayth) <hi>was made for</hi> (the good of) <hi>man, and not man for</hi> (the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of) <hi>the Sabbath:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar. 2.</hi> That he muſt be pinched with hunger, that hee muſt looſe his Oxe fallen into a pit, &amp; the like.</note> ſo that whenſoever it fell out, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it did, that mans good muſt be impaired, or the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath muſt be violated; the Sabbath ought rather to be violated, as being inferiour to the good of man, for which it was made and ordained.</p>
               <p>Such as will haue it the abſolute Law of Nature to ſanctifie one day in every weeke, of three thinges muſt affirme one. (.1.) Eyther they muſt ſay, that in caſe of neceſſity a man may not labour all the weeke: but this no man doth ſay, in my knowledg. (2) Or elſe they muſt ſay, that a man labouring all the weeke, doth ſanctifie one of the dayes: and this ſome ſeeme ready to affirme. But if to ſanctifie a day be to forbeare our owne worke, and to ſpend it in the ſervice of God: how doe I ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that day, which I ſpend about mine owne buſines. If
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7072:15"/> he that laboureth all day, may ſanctifie a <hi>Sabbath</hi> or <hi>Reſt:</hi> then he that feaſteth all day may ſanctifie a <hi>Faſt</hi> alſo. Moreover, I would demaund: When I labour hard e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day of the weeke about the ſame needfull buſines (ſuppoſe, repairing of the Sea bankes, defending a citty from the enemy, ſeeking cattell covered with ſnow &amp;c.) which of the dayes doe I ſanctifie? If I ſanctifie one, I may aſwell ſanctifie all: and then it ſeemeth I ought ſo to doe, as being the better (.3.) Or thirdly, they muſt ſay; that an abſolute law of Nature may be broken in caſe of neceſſity: but this againe I knowe none, that will ſay; though ſome affirme, that a law of Nature may be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by ſpeciall commandement from God thus the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites killed the Canaanites, and brake that law, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> But to ſpeake properly, the Iſraelites did not kill the Canaanites, but God killed them by the Iſraelites hands: <hi>ipſe non occidit, qui miniſterium debet iubenti,</hi> ſayth <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> it is the Iudge, and not the Executioner,<note place="margin">Aug: de Civitat.</note> that putteth a thiefe to death. In like ſort, to ſpeake properly the Iſraelites did not rob the Canaanites, nor the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians: for god whoſe <hi>the earth is,</hi> gaue vnto the Iſraelites the goods of them both. D. <hi>Field</hi> ſaith touching all the commandements excepting the fourth;<note place="margin">In the <hi>.5.</hi> booke: chap: <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>It is reſolued that God cannot permit a man to doe the things forbidden by them.</hi> Indeed, how ſhould God permit a man to doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt nature, as it was in his perfection? Whenſoeuer a law of nature is broken, Gods image, after which wee were created, is defaced in ſome meaſure and God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not permit, that his Image in vs ſhould be defaced.</p>
               <p>Now of this iudgement (among other great Divines)
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7072:16"/> M. <hi>Calvin</hi> was, I make no queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: thou maiſt perceaue by his manner of writing, that as he would not haue it morall, ſo neyther would he haue it the abſolute Law of Nature, to ſanctifie one day in every week. Thus he writeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Inſtitut: lib: 2. in 4 praecept.</bibl>
                  <p>Ita evaneſcunt nugae Pſeudoprophetatum, qui Iudaica opinione populum ſuperioribus ſeculis imbuerunt, nihil ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud afferentes niſi abrogatum eſſe quod cerimoniale erat in hoc mandato (id vocant ſua lingua diei ſeptimae taxationem) remanere autem quod morale eſt, nempe vnius diei obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem in hebdomade.<note n=".a." place="margin">
                        <hi>Calvin</hi> will not haue it morall to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie one day of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very weeke; which yet is the common doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine in theſe dayes.</note> Atqui id nihil aliud est, quam in Iudaeorum contumeliam diem mutare, diei ſanctitatem ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo eandem retinere:<note n=".b." place="margin">Againe, he will not haue the Lords day holy, as the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath was, that is, Sacramentally holy: but in theſe dayes ſome haue publiſhed, that there is aſmuch difference betweene the Lords day and other dayes of the weeke, as betweene Sacramentall bread, and common bread.</note> ſiquidem manet nobis etiamnum par myſterij in diebus ſignificatio, quae apud Iudaeos locum habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. Et ſanè videmus, quid tali doctrina profecerint: qui e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim eorum conſtitutionibus haerent, craſſa carnali<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiſmi ſuperſtitione Iudaeos ter ſuperant.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in a Sermon againſt obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of Newmoones.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:7072:16"/>
            <head>A DIALOGVE BETVVEENE A IEVV and a CHRISTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AN of the common Opinion.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Keepe the Sabbath, otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the name of Lords day.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1. Part.</hi> Here is ſhewed the difference betweene Iewes and Chriſtians about keeping the Sabbath.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>I keepe the Sabbath, as for your otherwiſe called, I finde it not in our Scriptures: will you chriſten the Sabbath with this new name? think you thereby to make it more and leſſe Jewiſh?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I keepe the Sabbath in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the fourth commandement in the Decalogue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>And I keep the Sabbath in obedience to the ſame Commandement.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I keepe not the Sabbath as a ſhadow of things to come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>Neither doe I ſo keep it: Moſes and the Prophets teach vs no ſuch thing, at leaſtwiſe in our vnderſtanding; as you may perceaue by thoſe many thouſands of our nation,<note place="margin">Act. 21.</note> who beleeuing in Chriſt, yet were zealous of the Law, which they would not haue beene, had they knowne, that the Sabbath,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7072:17"/> New moone &amp;c. were ſhadowes of things to come, and the body was of Chriſt, as ſince your Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> makes you beleeue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I keep the Sabbath on the firſt day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>I keepe the Sabbath on the ſeauenth day: and in ſo doing I fulfill the fourth commandement as well as you by your owne doctrine; and better in my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I forbeare all weeke-daie work, &amp; ſpend the Sabbath in the ſeruice of God, both in publike and in priuate</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>And I doe likewiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I dreſſe my dinner, and doe ſuch like workes on the Sabbath.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>I dare doe <hi>no worke,</hi> for ſo hath God charged, Exo. 20. &amp; I finde,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> that he himſelfe did none heretofore; he <hi>reſted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all his worke on the ſeauenth day.</hi> You Chriſtians indeed are bold to doe ſome worke: but take heed; for we know that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for gathering ſticks (not cutting down wood) was ſtoned to death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>We are as certaine, that we may doe ſuch workes, as wee are ſure Chriſt came into the world, and was crucified by you. You were often angry with him for his doings on the Sabbath; &amp; iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him not of God,<note place="margin">Ioh: 9.</note> becauſe he kept not the Sabbath, &amp; when opportunity ſerued, you nailed him to the croſſe; thinking happily that he being taken out of the way, the Sabbath ſhould be better kept in this reſpect. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you nailed him to the Croſſe,<note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> he nailed the handwriting of ordinances to the Croſſe alſo, and tooke it out of the way: ſince which time the Sabbath is not to be kept as before. You will one day repent your crucifying of Chriſt: for you did not only ſhed innocent blood; but alſo made the obſeruation of many things in your law ſinne vnto you. You bid vs take heed about our keeping
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7072:17"/> the Sabbath, but looke to your ſelues, you were beſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>Wherefore?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Part. 2.</hi> It is ſaid that the Iewes Sabbath was Ceremoniall in regard it was the ſeauenth day and here thou haſt ſome light, what to iudge of this doctrine.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>You keepe the Sabbath on the ſeauenth day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>Is it not ſaid in the fourth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, <hi>the ſeauenth day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God?</hi> Shall God haue two Sabbaths in one weeke? For the ſeuenth day muſt needs be ſtill his Sabbath, the day wherein he reſted. And ſuppoſe, that the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandement (as you teach) bindeth to ſanctifie one day in the weeke, doth it not binde to ſanctifie the ſeauenth day, as much as any other? Can you blame vs herein, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by your owne doctrine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Wee cannot blame you abſolutely for keeping the ſeauenth day: but you keepe it in obedience to the ceremoniall part of the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> commandement.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>I doe not well vnderſtand this: I pray explaine it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>J will the beſt I can: but I had rather you ſhould goe to ſome other, who can doe it better. The fourth Commandement is partly morall, &amp; partly Ceremoniall or ſhadowiſh: the morall part bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to ſanctifie one day of the weeke: the Ceremoniall or ſhadowiſh part bindeth to ſanctifie the ſeauenth day only. Now to ſanctifie the ſeauenth day in obedience to the morall part, is tolerable: but you keepe it in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the ſhadowiſh part, for you take your ſelues bound to ſanctifie the ſeauenth day alone: and ſo you keeping the ſeauenth day, obſerue a ſhadow; whereas did we keep the ſame day, we ſhould not; for we would keepe it in obedience to the morall part: and then wee might ſanctifie the ſeauenth day, as well as any other; vnleſſe happily, for ſome other conſiderations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>This doctrine is ſtrange to me: you ſpeake much
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7072:18"/> of <hi>Shadow,</hi> and <hi>ſhadowiſh:</hi> take heed this doctrine bee not rather <hi>ſhadowiſh</hi> then <hi>ſubſtantiall.</hi> Had your Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles taught ſuch doctrine in the Synagogues, I beleeue our Rabbins would haue ſmiled at it, neither would ſo many of our Nation haue followed them. To keep the Sabbath on the ſeauenth day, as not bound by the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Commandement to keepe it on that only day, is tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: but to keepe the Sabbath on the ſeauenth day, as bound by the fourth Commandement to keepe it on that only day, is to obſerue a ſhadow. This is very nice doctrine: Well, haue you any thing elſe to ſay, wherein we are to blame?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3. Part.</hi> It is ſaid, that the ſtrict reſt was Ceremoniall: &amp; here thou haſt ſome light, what to iudge of this doctrine alſo. <hi>Numb. 15.</hi>
                  </note>Yes. You forbeare to dreſſe meat, and to doe ſuch like workes on the Sabbath: for which (were there nothing elſe) Chriſt at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to iudgement would caſt you into hell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>Did not your Chriſt giue out, that he was the ſonne of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and ſo he is: what of that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>God put a man to death in this world, becauſe he did gather ſtickes on the Sabbath: and will the ſonne of God caſt vs into hell, becauſe wee doe not gather ſtickes, kindle a fire, and dreſſe meat therein?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>That he will: for this ſtrict reſt was ſhadowiſh al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. Jt hath beene an olde ſaying, that the Ceremonies ought to haue ſome time to be honeſtly buried: but now it is too long to keepe them aboue ground; they ſtinke by this time. And leaſt you ſhould maruell, that I ſay, Chriſt wil condemne you for your manner of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Sabbath; knowe, that to obſerue a ſhadow, is to denie after a ſort, that he came into the world. Jt is too much by word to denie the ſonne of <hi>Mary</hi> the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7072:18"/> to be the Chriſt; but you denie it by your deeds al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as long as you obſerue a ſhadow. A Father of our Church, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> by name (whom wee eſteeme as much as you doe any of your Rabbins) ſpeaking of the Sabbath, doth ſay, <hi>Whoſoeuer keepeth that day, as the letter ſoundeth, ſauoreth of the fleſh;</hi> &amp; ſuch are yee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>Though we keepe the Sabbath according to the letter (as by your leaue ſome Chriſtians alſo doe in their vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) yet we keepe it not as a ſhadow, as I ſaid before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>That's nothing in my opinion: you keepe it in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the ſhadowiſh part of the fourth comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. You keepe not circumciſion neither as a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow: and put caſe beſide, that you did not obſerue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely the eight day, and more, that you did not cut off all the foreskinne: yet this would not excuſe you from obſeruing a ſhadow. As neither ſhall it excuſe thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs (for ſome ſuch I feare there are) who though they keepe not the Feaſt of Whitſuntide as a Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, neither at the ſame time, nor altogether in the ſame manner, as you doe; yet through ignorance keepe it in obedience to that your law, Leuit. 23. For this is euen all in all, to obſerue any day, time, meat, &amp;c. in obedience to a ſhadowiſh Commandement: which I deſire you, and thoſe of my brethren, whom it may concerne, to conſider well off; and ſo, Fare yee well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, I pray, be not ſo haſty. I may become a Chriſtian, and then ſome doubt may trouble my mind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>What is that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay, that the ſtrict reſt is ſhadowiſh: and by your doctrine he which reſteth too ſtrictly, obſerueth a ſhadow; for he doth it in obedience
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7072:19"/> to the ceremoniall part of the fourth commandement, miſtaking it for the moral. I would now demand of you, whether he doth not reſt too ſtrictly, who forbeareth that worke on the Sabbath, which is not forbidden by the moral part of the fourth commandement?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Yes; for that worke is forbidden by the ceremoniall part. All worke is forbidden by the fourth commandement: now the greater workes are forbidden by the morall part; and the leſſer, by the ceremoniall part: and where the moral part ceaſeth to forbid, there the ceremoniall part begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to forbid; as I conceaue by this our common di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>Me thinks you Chriſtians are here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Scylla and Charibdis: you can hardly chuſe, but either breake the morall part, or fulfill the ceremoniall part of the fourth commandement. I pray ſhew mee, how I may rightly diſcerne the partition; for there muſt needes bee very little difference betweene ſome workes forbidden by the morall part, and other forbidden by the ceremoniall. Againe, whereas I perceaue by your words erwhile, that to forbeare dreſſing of meat, is to reſt too ſtrictly, and to fulfill the ceremoniall part: I would learne of you, whether about dreſſing of meat, I need not feare breaking the morall part?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, you may labour as hard about dreſſing meat, as at plow; or you may beſtow too much time thereabout; and thus breake the morall part. Againe, I muſt tell you, that you may dreſſe meat, and yet fulfill the ceremonial part: for you may ſeeth an Egge, and refuſe to ſeeth Fleſh; &amp; ſo reſt two ſtrictly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iew.</speaker>
               <p>It is needfull then, that you define preciſely, what meat may be dreſſed, in what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7072:19"/> how long I may be about it, how hard I may labour thereabout, whether vntil I ſweat or not: ſo, for ſeruing cattle; whether I may carry burthens of fodder into the field, how big burthens I may carry, how farre I may carry them &amp;c. and ſo, for many other matters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I maruell that our learned men, who haue written ſo largely vpon the fourth commandement, haue not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter canvaſed this matter; to ſay nothing, that they doe not agree among themſelues. But I can ſtay no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger with you: only I ſay, when you become a Chriſtian, if you come to me, you ſhall haue my beſt adviſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>A note touching the Lords day.</head>
            <p>I Knowe not any learned and godly Divine, but will acknowledge, that the Lords daie is of great antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and had his beginning from ſome of the Apoſtles: but if any man would haue vs beleeue, that Chriſt did inſtitute it, and that from the time of his reſurrection, it hath beene generally obſerued of the faithfull; hee muſt bring better proofe, then hitherto I haue ſeene any.</p>
            <p>The Church of Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſted of Iewes &amp; Gentiles: and as touching the beleeuing Jewes at Jeruſalem, it is out of queſtion, that for many yeares they obſerued the ſame day as before: for they were zealous of the Law, one part whereof was the obſeruation of the ſeauenth daie.<note place="margin">Act. 21.20.</note> If Baptiſme would not ſerue them inſteed of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7072:20"/> who can beleeue, that the Lords daie would ſerue them inſteed of the Sabbath? Nether is it to bee maruelled, that they were zealous of the Law, when as <hi>Iames</hi> and the Elders did not ſo much as teach them, that the law of commandements contained in ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, was aboliſhed; as is manifeſt in that they deſired S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> to make it appeare by his practiſe,<note place="margin">Act 21.24.</note> that the report of him was nothing, &amp; that he himſelfe alſo walked or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlie, and kept the Law. But were they zealous of the Sabbath, or not: ſeeing the vnbeleeuing Jewes were ſo angrie with Chriſt afore time for the carriage of a bed on the Sabbath,<note place="margin">Ioh 5.</note> and at this time with S. <hi>Paul</hi> for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of the Temple,<note place="margin">Act. 21.28.</note> as they ſuppoſed; it cannot be, that they would ſuffer their Sabbath, and other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidaies to be prophaned by Chriſtians, as long as their commonweale ſtood. The Church then at Jeruſalem a long time obſerued the Sabbath or ſeauenth daie: and now that beſides the Sabbath, and other holidaies inioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the law, they ſanctified the Lords daie, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted from worke two daies in every weeke; I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue without ſome proofe, and hitherto I haue ſeene none at all.</p>
            <p>As touching the Churches of the Gentiles: it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by the Scriptures, that ſome of them for a time came together rather on the Iewes Sabbath, then on any other daie: indeed S. <hi>Paul,</hi> as he yeelded leſſe to the Jewes then other, ſo happilie in the Churches by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe eſtabliſhed, hee beganne ſooner then other to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point their meetings on the firſt daie of the week; which daie growing more &amp; more in requeſt, before the yeare
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7072:20"/> 96, obtained the name of <hi>Lords day:</hi> which name had it beene giuen, when S. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote his firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians, S. <hi>Luke</hi> the Acts, it is likely, that one of them would haue vſed it; and yet it is not vnlikely, that this name <hi>(Lords day)</hi> was giuen, as ſoone as the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be in any great account.</p>
            <p>Now, about this <hi>Lords Day,</hi> the firſt day of the weeke (commonly called Sunday) there are in theſe times three opinions ſomething differing the one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <div n="1" type="opinion">
               <head>1 <hi>Opinion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It is the will and command of God, that Chriſtians ſhould ſanctifie one daie of euery weeke: &amp; as he bound the Iſraelites heretofore to ſanctifie the Sabbath or ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day; ſo in this time of the Goſpell hee bindeth vs Chriſtians to ſanctifie the Lords day, or firſt daie of the weeke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="opinion">
               <head>2 <hi>Opinion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It is the will and command of God, that Chriſtians ſhould ſanctifie one day of euery weeke: but whereas he bound the Iſraelites heretofore to ſanctifie the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day alone; hee left it to the Chriſtian Church to chuſe their day, and it hath choſen the Lords day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="opinion">
               <head>3 <hi>Opinion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Redemp. in <hi>4</hi> praecep.</note>
               </head>
               <p>It is the will and command of God to ſanctifie <hi>ſome time, aliquam temporis partem,</hi> as <hi>Zanchius</hi> ſpeaketh: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this time ſhall be, God left to the Chriſtian Church to appoint, and it hath appointed the Lords day.</p>
               <p>Of the former opinion, I ſcarce knowe any Divines of note, vnleſſe of late yeares: betweene the two latter
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7072:21"/> opinions there is in reſpect of vs little or no difference at all, for by both the Lords day is the command of God mediatly; God mediatly, and by the Magiſtrate bindeth vs Chriſtians to ſanctifie the Lords day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>Obiect.</head>
               <p>Then the Gouernours of the Church may alter the day; yea, they may appoint the firſt of one weeke, the third of the next, the fift of the next &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſw.</head>
                  <p>It doth not follow: for the beſt order is the will of God, and law of Nature. The Gouernours then can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſet downe what order they will, neither touching the time and place of Gods worſhip, neither touching other things belonging therevnto: but what in their vnderſtanding is the beſt order, they are bound to ſet downe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>Obiect.</head>
               <p>If God mediatly, and by the Magiſtrate bindeth vs Chriſtians to ſanctifie the Lords day: certainely, this bond is ſo weake, that very many will eaſily breake it.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſw.</head>
                  <p>This bond is ſtrong enough to hold him, that is not very vnruly. In the fift of <hi>Marke</hi> we read of one, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing often bound with fetters and chaines, brake them in peeces; no <hi>Man</hi> could binde him ſtrong enough: but when Chriſt had caſt out the euill Spirit, they <hi>ſee him</hi> (ſaith the text) <hi>ſitting,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 5.15.</note> 
                     <hi>cloathed, and in his right minde.</hi> In like ſort, deliuer theſe vnruly fellowes from the evil Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, be a meanes to bring them into their right minde, &amp; afterward (J doubt not) the Gouernours of the Church
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7072:21"/> ſhall binde them well enough. They will ſit ſtill, bee quiet, and be content to be ruled by reaſon: they wil ſee by the light of nature, that as there are feet, ſo there muſt be an head, of the body; and that the feet cannot ſay to the head, <hi>We haue no need of thee;</hi> without the helpe of the head they cannot chuſe the beſt way: they wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member by whom kings raigne, that all power is from aboue; and that as <hi>God hath ſet the members euery one in the body, as it pleaſed him; ſo hath he ſet ſome in the Church,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.18.28.</note> 
                     <hi>firſt Apoſtles ſecondarily Prophets, thirdly teachers, &amp;c.</hi> This and much more will they call to minde, when they are brought into their right minde, and very willing ſhall we haue them to be ordered.</p>
                  <p>What thinke we? Had ſuch vnruly fellowes liued vnder the law (and,<note place="margin">Note, that even in the time of the law ſome things were left to be ordered by the Magiſtrate.</note> 
                     <hi>lex à ligando</hi>) had they beene bound ſtrong enough? Nay verily: for though God appointed the preciſe daie, and commanded to haue an <hi>holy Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:</hi> yet, no time of the day for this Convocation, not two Convocations, not Synagogues. When they had beene called,<note place="margin">This commande of Paul, or law of Nature, is the generall, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the fourth common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement in the Decalogue, and all other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements touching the time and place of Gods worſhip and other things belonging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto.</note> they would haue anſwered with <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram, We will not come:</hi> for God himſelfe hath not bidden vs come to ſuch a place, nor at ſuch time of the day.</p>
                  <p>Let the law of Nature be no more, then all acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>to ſanctifie ſome time,</hi> as the Gentiles did: ſuppoſe, no other command but that of <hi>Paul, Let all things bee done to edifying, decently, and in order.</hi> If there come a command from authority to ſanctifie any day of the weeke, yea beſides the Lords day; this is enough to bind him, that is in his right minde: if any wilfully breake this
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7072:22"/> bond,<note place="margin">Iud. ver. 8.</note> it is by the comming of another Spirit vpon him then came vpon Sampſon heretofore. It were good to beware, leaſt any of vs bee found ſuch as <hi>Iude</hi> ſpeaketh of, <hi>Deſpiſing gouernment, &amp; ſpeaking euill of dignities:</hi> for it is too much to deſpiſe Governours; but more, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe gouernment it ſelfe. Certainely if any man bee ſo vnruly, that Gods Miniſters and Officers here bee not able to binde him; God hath other officers and ſeruants elſewhere, which are able; <hi>And the King ſaid to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Take him and binde him hand and foot, and caſt him into vtter darkneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To make an end. They which ſay leaſt, ſay enough to cauſe all thoſe, who haue the feare of God before their eyes, to ſanctifie the Lords day: and they which ſay moſt, doe not ſay enough to cauſe thoſe, who feare not God, to forbeare driuing pack-horſes therein, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting the Tauerne, and the like. Would to God, no man might once ſay more nor leſſe than the truth; for doubtleſſe were the truth alone preached, the greateſt good would follow therevpon: and this is one matter more, which cauſeth me, &amp; ſhould cauſe thee (Gentle Reader) often and earneſtly to pray in this manner, or to this effect; <hi>Lord haue mercy vpon vs, and incline our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours hearts to take ſuch order, that once at length we may be all brought to the right vnderſtanding of the fourth Commandement.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:7072:22"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 1. line 8. <hi>ſtrike out,</hi> had p. 3. l. 4. <hi>ſtrike out</hi> your. p. 5. l. 4. <hi>for</hi> here likeneth, <hi>read</hi> here he likeneth. p. 5. l. 16. text <hi>read</hi> type. p. 6. <hi>in marg.</hi> If the Sabbath were a ſhadow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 9. l. worke <hi>r.</hi> weeke. p. 10. l. 16. <hi>after</hi> Remember the Sabbath to ſanctifie it, <hi>read</hi> this ſhould be a more generall commandement, then if hee had ſaid, Remember the ſeauenth day to ſanctifie it. p. 12. l. 3. vs <hi>r.</hi> me. p. 18. l. 3. commanding, <hi>r.</hi> commanded. p. 26. The ſaying of Chryſoſtome ſhould be placed laſt of all, after the note touching the Lords day. p. 27. l. 7. to make it more Chriſtian and leſſe Iewiſh. <hi>Other faults eſcaped in printing the Reader may amend.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
